William F.J. Boardman papers
Connecticut Historical Society
William F.J. Boardman Papers
1864-1899
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Boardman, William Francis Joseph
1 linear foot (2 boxes)
Biographical Sketch
William Francis Joseph Boardman (1828-1912) was the scion of a prosperous and influential Connecticut family. His ancestor Samuel Boreman (1615-1678), originally of Oxfordshire, England, was one of the early settlers of Wethersfield, Connecticut. W.F.J. Boardman's father, William Boardman (1805-1887), founder of the family's coffee, tea, and spice business, was a printer, founder and editor of the Norwich Republican (1828-1829), state prison director, member of the legislature, banker and insurance director, merchant and manufacturer. William Boardman married Mary Francis (1803-1884) of Wethersfield and had, besides William Francis Joseph, three children: Thomas Jefferson (1832-1858), known as Jeff; Mary Lucinda (1841-1934), known as Lizzie; and Emma Jennette (1846-1860).
W.F.J. Boardman was born on December 12, 1828 in the old Boardman house in Wethersfield and received his education in Wethersfield's public schools. In 1846, he joined his father's business, and when the business moved to Hartford, he became a partner in Boardman and Son. In 1853, his brother Thomas Jefferson also became a partner of the business now named Boardman and Sons. The business, located on Asylum Avenue, maintained a large-scale wholesale trade in New England and other regions. After his health failed, W.F.J. attempted to recuperate during a trip to Europe and the southern United States. Unable to fully regain his health, he retired in 1888, after forty-two years in business. He died on November 23, 1912 and was buried in Hartford's Cedar Hill Cemetery.
W.F.J. Boardman was very active in the civic affairs of Hartford. He was an original member of hte Putnam Phalanx, a military organization of Connecticut. He ws a member of the Hartford Common Council, incolved in the highways and railroads of Connecticut. In 1862 he was a director of the State Bank of Hartford. He also undertook business interests in the Hartford and New York Steamboat Company, the Merrick Thread Company of Holyoke, as well as paper and water power companies. He was a life member of the Connecticut Historical Society, and a member of the Sons of the American Revolution. W.F.J. Boardman conducted intensive genealogical research on the Boardman family. In 1895, he published the Boardman Genealogy 1525-1855 and the Ancestry of William Francis Joseph Boardman in 1906.
On January 7, 1852, W.F.J. married Jane Maria Greenleaf (1835-1899), a member of the prominent Greenleaf families of Massachusetts and Connecticut. Jane Boardman pursued numerous charitable works in Hartford. They resided at 74 Farmington Avenue, in a house that contained valuable paintings, furniture, family records and artifacts, and a personal library of over 1000 volumes. Their son, William Greenleaf Boardman (1853-1908), worked for Boardman and Sons but had to retire from business due to eye problems. On October 29, 1874 William married Eliza Root, whose mother was a cousin of the poet John Greenleaf Whittier. Their children were Francis Whittier (1876-1885), Cedric Root (1886-1960) and Dorothy Root (1889-1945). The family resided in Hartford.
Scope and Content
The Boardman collection consists of William Francis Joseph's diaries, memoranda and account notebooks, a song collection, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous papers and clippings. Six of the diaries were kept by Mr. Boardman's mother, Mary Francis Boardman. In spite of his economic prosperity and high standing in the community, the diaries reveal Mr. Boardman's melancholy turn of mind and his preoccupation with his wife's constant illnesses. Throughout his entries, Mr. Boardman details the various afflictions in his lungs, kidneys, heart, and bowels, as well as attacks of boils and carbuncles. Both he and his wife, Jane, suffered from insomnia and nervousness. He often reflects on man's mortality and the approaching loss of his parents and contemporaries. He repeatedly mentions his depression in terms of "feeling blue" or "used up." This state of mind is in contrast to his appreciation of the beloved family circle, his lovely home, and his many civic interests and engaged comments on current events in America and abroad. His diaries also contain commentary, facts, and statistics on Hartford businesses and the economic environment of the state.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Boardman, Mary Francis, 1803-1884.
Subjects
Depressed persons -- Connecticut -- Hartford.; Genealogy; Mortality
Genre Forms
Diaries -- 1864-1899; Diaries -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- 1864-1899
Contents:
- I. Diaries and Memoranda Books
  - 1868
    - from New England Ners, New Haven County: "A colored man named "Caesar,"w ho recently died at the almshousein Waterburyi s said to have been the last relic of slavery in tiis state."
    - February2 4, 1868: W.F.J.d iscussetsh e impeachmenotf PresidenJt ohnson'
    - Four photographso f campm eetingo n Martha's Vineyad in August
    - August4, 1868: W.F.J.'sb rotherJ effs daughteMr innied ied
    - W.F.J. expressesd eepb elief in heaven.
    - Capital, assetsa, nd dividendso finsurance companiesli sted'
  - 1870
    - January 31, 1870: summary of important events in and around Hartford; deathsb, uildingsp. rofit s of insumncec ompanies
    - August1 2,1 870: W.F.J.d iscussems urderc aseo fCapt. William Willard by Wilson, the robber of Brown & Thompson.
    - November 22, 1870: "The Parting Hours" and W. F, J.'s thoughts on mortality
    - W. F. J. discussesR econstructionu nder Gmnt and the FEnco-Prussian War.
  - 1871
    - W.F.J. remembers [his sister's] Emma's death ll years ago in 1860 and the year 1868, when he left for Florida to recover ftom illness.
    - October 4, 1871: Brigham Young arrested for bigamy.
    - October 9, l87l: W. F. J. discusses the Great Chicago Fire.
    - End of diary contains accounts, rents, sales, etc.
  - January 1, 1876 - August 5, 1876
    - April 24,1876t W. F, J. discussesim peachmenot f PresidentJ ohnson
    - July 6, 1876: [General] Custer killed
  - January 1, 1877 - March 22, 1877, Actual last entry March 21, 1877
  - March 22, 1877 - July 1, 1877, Actual last entry July 3, 1877
  - July 1, 1877 - October 21, 1877
    - July 26,1877:. discusses the great stike of 1877
    - Ssptember4, 1877: "Bdgham Young leff [$] 2,000,000t o be divided up